Henry D. Gray Papers 1984.0009
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Henry D. Gray Papers
undated, 1953-1970
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0009
12 Linear Feet
Born on January 18, 1908, Henry Gray studied at Pomona College. In 1933 he received a B.D. from the Hartford Theological Seminary and later earned a Ph.D. at the University of Edinburgh. Gray helped found churches around the world. Reverend Gray ministered at South Congregational Church in Hartford for 15 years. He was a member of the Hartford Commission on the City Plan and retired in 1970.
Biography
The Reverend Henry David Gray was born January 18, 1908 in Antrim, Northern Ireland, to Nathaniel and Margaret Gray. He studied at Pomona College in California until 1930, and later received a B.D. from the Hartford Theological Seminary in 1933. He also took the Ph.D. from the University of Edinburgh in 1935. In 1930, Rev. Gray married Helen Lorbeer. The couple had three children, David, Ellen and Betsey.
After holding positions as minister in Scotland, Massachusetts, and California, Rev. Gray relocated to Hartford, Connecticut. In 1956, he was installed as the 14th minister of South Congregational Church in Hartford, which was founded in 1670. Rev. Gray stayed on as minister there until 1970, when he retired in favor of the Rev. John R. Elmore.
Rev. Gray's 15 years at South Congregational were distinguished. He ran a radio show, guided the renovation of the church, and was very active in youth programs. In addition, he helped to found churches in other areas of Connecticut and around the world. Another important position held by Rev. Gray was member of the Hartford Commission on the City Plan. He took this position in 1959, and served as chairman of the commission for several years. The commission was involved in various aspects of urban planning and renewal for the city.
Rev. Gray was also an author. The most notable among the many books and articles wasere The Upward Call, which became a best-seller. Upon his retirement in 1970, Rev. Gray planned to continue writing and working in civic affairs.
Scope and Content
The Henry D. Gray Papers contain administrative and research materials pertaining to the Hartford Commission on the City Plan.
Arrangement
Series I: City Plan Files (undated, 1959-1970), consists of material relating to the Hartford Commission on the City Plan. The greater bulk of this material is made up of the minutes and agendas of the commission's meetings. There are other items as well, like inter-office memoranda and reports on various issues. The arrangement of this series is chronological. Undated papers that were found with a group of papers from a particular year were placed with those papers in files marked "undated".
Series II: Subject Files, (undated) contains folders that were marked with headings by Gray. They are organized alphabetically, and most of them pertain to topics about the city of Hartford. One folder, called General Plan, contained a map of an unknown region.
Series III: Research Files, (undated, 1953-1958) is composed of a variety of publications. The publications treat different aspects of urban planning and community renewal, with an emphasis on the city of Hartford and the state of Connecticut. Many of the items are annotated. In addition, there are several items from this series which, because of their large size, had to be placed apart in a larger container (Box 10). Also, it should be noted that there is one folder of "Curia dixit" pamphlets from 1953 to 1958. Other copies of "Curia dixit" from later years are interspersed within the City Plan Files series. The folders of Research Files are arranged alphabetically.
Custodial History
Carl Abbot, of the School of Urban Affairs at Portland State University, acquired the papers from Reverend Gray.
Acquisition Information
The Henry D. Gray papers were donated by Carl Abbot in 1984.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Administrative records; Publications (documents); Community development; Clergy; Hartford (inhabited place); City planning; Urban renewal; Connecticut (state)
- Series I: City Plan Files, undated, 1959-1970
  - 1959 May - August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1959 September - November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1959 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1960 January - February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1960 March - April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1960 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1960 June - September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1960 October - December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1961 January - February (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1961 March (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1961 April - May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1961 June - July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1961 August - September (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1961 October - November (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1961 December, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1962 January - February (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1962 April (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1962 May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1962 June (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1962 July (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1962 August (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1962 September (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1962 October (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1962 November (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1962 December (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1963 January - February (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1963 March - April (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1963 June - July (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1963 August - September (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 1963 October (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1963 November - December (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1964 January (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1964 February (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1964 March (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1964 April (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 1964 May (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1964 June - July (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1964 August (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 1964 September (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 1964 October - November (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1964 December (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 1965 January - February (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 1965 March (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 1965 April - May (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1965 June - July (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 1965 August - September (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - 1965 October (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - 1965 November (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - 1965 December (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - 1966 January - February (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - 1966 March (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - 1966 April - May (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - 1966 June (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - 1966 August (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - 1966 September (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - 1966 October (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - 1966 November (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - 1966 December (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - 1967 January (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - 1967 February (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - 1967 March (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - 1967 April (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - 1967 May (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - 1967 June (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - 1967 July (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - 1967 August (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - 1967 September (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - 1967 October (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - 1967 November (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - 1967 December (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - 1968 January (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - 1968 February - March (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - 1968 April (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - 1968 May (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - 1968 June (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - 1968 July (Box 4, Folder 81-83)
  - 1968 August (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - 1968 August (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - 1968 September (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - 1968 October (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - 1968 November (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - 1968 December (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - 1969 January - July (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - 1969 August - September (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - 1969 October (Box 4, Folder 92-93)
  - 1969 November (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - 1969 December (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - 1970 January - February (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - 1970 March (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - 1970 April (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - 1970 May (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - 1970 June (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - 1970 July (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - 1970 August (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - 1970 September (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - 1970 October (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 105)
- Series II: Subject Files, undated
  - Bushnell Park-State Center (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Capitol Center (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Coliseum (Box 5, Folder 108-109)
  - Connecticut Federation Planning (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Constitution Plaza (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Development (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Flood Control (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Government and Development (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Hartford Center Comm. (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Hartford, Committee for (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Housing Comm. (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Neighborhood Planning Association (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Parking (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Plan Director (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Plan Director (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Plan Staff (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Plan Staff (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - Reference (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - Regional Planning (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - South Main (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - South Village (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - UConn and Redevelopment (Box 5, Folder 129)
- Series III: Research Files, undated, 1953-1958
  - Hartford Administration Organization (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Albany Avenue (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Background Studies (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Background Studies (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Background Studies (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Capital Improvement Program (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - Capitol Center (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - Capitol Center (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Capitol Region Planning Agency (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Capitol Region Planning Agency (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Capitol Region Planning Agency (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Capitol Region Planning Agency (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - Hartford Catalogs (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Charter Oak Neighborhood (Box 6, Folder 144)
  - Hartford Churches (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - Hartford Churches (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - City Plan By-Laws (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - Colt Park (Box 6, Folder 148)
  - Community Development Action Plan (Box 6, Folder 149)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - Community Renewal Program/Hartford (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Community Renewal Program/Other cities (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Community Renewal Program/Other cities (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Connecticut Board of Education (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Connecticut: Choices for Action (Box 7, Folder 160-161)
  - Connecticut: Developing Community (Box 7, Folder 162-164)
  - Curia dixit, 1953-1958 (Box 8, Folder 165)
  - Day Care (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Downtown Hartford (Box 8, Folder 167-169)
  - Hartford Economy (Box 8, Folder 170-172)
  - Connecticut Government (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Housing (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Housing (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Nuisance Use (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Park Improvement (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Park Street (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Parking (Box 8, Folder 179-180)
  - Hartford Planning and Development (Box 8, Folder 181-182)
  - Hartford Schools (Box 9, Folder 183-184)
  - Three Institutions Area (Box 9, Folder 185)
  - Town Meeting for Tomorrow (Box 9, Folder 186-187)
  - Traffic and Transportation (Box 9, Folder 188)
  - Trumbull Street Area (Box 9, Folder 189)
  - Urban Renewal (Box 9, Folder 190)
  - Zoning (Box 9, Folder 191-195)
  - A Coliseum for Hartford (Box 10, Folder 196)
  - Hartford, Connecticut Interim Plan for Downtown (Box 10, Folder 197)
  - Preliminary Housing Plan (Box 10, Folder 198)
  - Preliminary Transportation Plan (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - Southside Hartford Connecticut (Box 10, Folder 200)